<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The foot out of the snare. Or, A restoration of the inhabitants of Zion into their place, after their bewildered and lost estate by the operation of a violent power, and authority, wrought in the author by the Prince of Darkness, under an appearance of the brightest light. Being a brief declaration of his entrance into that sect, called (by the name of) Quakers. With a short discourse relating what judgment he was learned in, by the ministry of those people. Together with the revelation of a spirit in himself. Also, what desperate delusions he was led into by yielding a subjection to the teachings of a seducing spirit in him under a shadow of the true light; and how this body of deceipt came to be destroyed. With the manner of his separation from them. / By me John Toldervy, then servant to Col. Webb.</title>
            <author>Toldervy, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E861_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206654</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865770</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865770</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118021</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94717)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118021)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 130:E861[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The foot out of the snare. Or, A restoration of the inhabitants of Zion into their place, after their bewildered and lost estate by the operation of a violent power, and authority, wrought in the author by the Prince of Darkness, under an appearance of the brightest light. Being a brief declaration of his entrance into that sect, called (by the name of) Quakers. With a short discourse relating what judgment he was learned in, by the ministry of those people. Together with the revelation of a spirit in himself. Also, what desperate delusions he was led into by yielding a subjection to the teachings of a seducing spirit in him under a shadow of the true light; and how this body of deceipt came to be destroyed. With the manner of his separation from them. / By me John Toldervy, then servant to Col. Webb.</title>
                  <author>Toldervy, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Tho. Brewster, at the Three Bibles, neer the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656. [i.e. 1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Thomason apparently received his copy in 1655.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 24:"; the 6 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118021:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Foot out of the Snare.</hi> OR, A Reſtoration of the inhabitants of <hi>Zion</hi> into their Place, after their bewildered and loſt Eſtate by the Operation of a violent Power, and Authority, wrought in the Author by the Prince of Darkeſs, under an Appearance of the brighteſt Light.</p>
            <p>BEING A Brief <hi>Declaration</hi> of his entrance into that <hi>Sect,</hi> Called (by the Name of) QUAKERS.</p>
            <p>With a ſhort <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> relating what Judgment he was learned in, by the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of thoſe People.</p>
            <p>Together with the Revelation of a <hi>Spirit</hi> in himſelf.</p>
            <p>Alſo, what <hi>Deſperate Deluſions</hi> he was led into by yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a ſubjection to the Teachings of a Seducing Spirit in him under a ſhadow of the true Light; and how this Body of Deceipt came to be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>With the manner of his Separation from them.</p>
            <p>By me <hi>John Toldervy,</hi> then Servant to Col. <hi>Webb.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord-God, Behold, I lay in Zion for a Foundation a Stone, a tryed Stone, a precious Corner-ſtone, a ſure Foundation: he that believeth ſhall not make haſte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore hear the word of the Lord, ye ſcornful men that Rule this People which is in Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This thy Brother was dead, and is alive; was loſt, and is found.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.C.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Brewſter,</hi> at the Three Bibles, neer the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118021:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118021:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIEND,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">U</seg>Pon a Preſumption that thou art One, whoſe Minde is (in ſome meaſure) fitted for Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and not of thoſe, who are Reſolved into Self, and Hardened againſt any Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery which might effect to the enlightning of their Underſtanding, where their own Weakneſs, Fancy, and Imagination, hath formed it ſelf in them: (which depraved Condition I ſadly witneſſed ſomtime to have been mine own.) At which time, though any Perſon whatſoever (yea, were it poſſible to have been an Angel from Heaven that ſhould have attempted me with any Information, contrary to my Eſpouſed and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged Fancy and Imagination, I ſhould have concluded ſuch a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger and Meſſage, unreſiſtably Accurſed: And (through the depravedneſs of my Underſtanding) adjudged it to have been the Spirit
<pb facs="tcp:118021:3"/>of God in me which had ſo concluded. If this Diſcourſe ſhould come into the hands of any ſuch Perſon or Perſons (as ſuch there are too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) I expect but little Fruit upon their accompt; but they are by me pitied, for as much as their Bondage and Captivity is Great and much to be lamented, though the God of Truth can restore a ſound Minde, and a cleer Underſtanding unto ſuch who by their own Righteouſneſs, under a ſeeming appearance of Self-Denial, have made themſelves Servants to other gods. And when this power of God is made known, that they might be Guided in one Worſhip of one God living in them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, they ſhall admire and magnifie that gracious Arm by which they were made Free, as I do this day; and then this Diſcourſe will not be unſutable, or unpleaſing unto them. In the mean time, to ſuch, whoſe Minds are Free and not Entangled; I would give an Accompt briefly of the Matter, but chiefly the Occaſion of this enſuing Diſcourſe, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with my Intent and Scope therein: though the ſubject Matter doth relate principally to the Perſons, who go under the Name of <hi>Quakers,</hi> (as being ſo diſtinguiſhed amongſt men) and of the Effects which were wrought in, and by me, through the Guidance and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of a Seducing Spirit in me, under a pretence of Light, yet is not my Scope to traduce the Perſons, nor to incenſe the Powers or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, Miniſters, or People, againſt them: For I know many of whom they are not known, have abuſed the Truth, by ſeeking to Defend themſelves in that deceipt which that Spirit (that is of God in them) hath witneſſed againſt; by which the generality of men, are (through their miſguided Spirits, are already beyond meaſure) bitterly incenſed againſt them.</p>
            <p>Touching the Occaſion: It is not unknown to many; yea, I ſay, to many in and about this City of <hi>London,</hi> That I was in an eminent way, as a firſt Fruits of thoſe who gave up themſelves to thoſe Wayes, and Teachings, wherein I profited not a little: nor went I on with a ſlow pace: But I confeſs, ſuch was the fire of zeal which burned within me, that by it I was over-powered and hastily Acted forth without Knowledge: (I mean, ſuch Knowledge as was according to God) but ſuch as my Teachers held forth in ſome meaſure I abounded in, (as the Diſcourſe it ſelf will witneſs) but the tendency thereof in the General was to Folly and Madneſs; as I by ſad Experience witneſs in my meaſure: But God, who is rich in Mercy, through his great Love wherewith he hath loved me, hath magnified the ſame in opening mine
<pb facs="tcp:118021:3"/>eyes, and turned me from the Darkneſs, wherewith I was bewildered, and benighted; even to Aſtoniſhment and Admiration: Having opened my Mouth, and put a new Song into it of Praiſes to his Name, in deſpight of all thoſe cruel denountiations of Woe, and Plagues, which have been pronounced againſt me (even to Eternity) ſince my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture and Separation from them; by ſome of thoſe who could once have put me into their Boſomes, whom I, nevertheleſs, patiently bear within Love, having better Perſwaſions towards them.</p>
            <p>It having therefore pleaſed the Father to Reſcue and Deliver my Soul out of this deep Pit, and raiſed me up, and ſet me as a living Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of his Praiſe, beyond expectation. I durſt not ſhut up in Silence the marvelous Wiles, and deep Deceipts, and Devices, which the Enemy had upon me, through which I have been carried, and from whence through Mercy Redeemed, that I might tell to Others how bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God hath dealt with me, remembring me in my low Eſtate; for his Mercy endureth for ever.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> To which end therefore, that I might make known my Duty of Praiſe and Thanks to God, for the Riches of his Love towards me; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, to expreſs my tenderneſs towards my Brethren, my Companions in the Bond of Love, who are environed in the ſame Circle and Maze, kept in Bondage by their own miſguided Spirits, ſubjected to Lawes and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, Ceremonies and Traditions of their own Inventing; to which they are nevertheleſs in ſo great Subjection, as amounts to Eternal Death, and Wrath, and Firy Indignation upon the Breath thereof: Of which may be ſaid, Who hath required theſe things at your hands?</p>
            <p>May not this be a Word in ſeaſon to ſome, by which they might be perſwaded at leaſt to Debate the Matter with their own Souls, and to Conſider where they are, and who requires theſe things wherein they are ſo prepoſtrouſly Zealous; denying themſelves their Juſt and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Liberty out of a ſlaviſh Fear: but there is ſuch a Reſolvedneſs, that I can ſcarce conceive that this might be ſucceſsful to many, yet the power of Truth can overturn all things which exalteth it ſelf under a ſhadow of Good, as being maintained by a Lye.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That the Example of my Zeal, and Forwardneſs of Minde without ſerious Conſideration and Examination, taking all for Truth, affecting thoſe Notinal Apprehenſions, which (in that Way) I was then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb facs="tcp:118021:4"/>with: (By which true Judgement became loſt in me.) That I may in this, be as a Sea-mark, whoſe poor Veſſel was well-nigh Split up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe Rocks; and am now become as one to give warning that none do, (through the haſtineſs of their own Minds) in their own Wills, under a pretence of God's Will, diſhonor the Truth, by giving heed to ſuch Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducings and Temptations: aſcribing that to God, and calling it His, when indeed it is the Effects of their own Fancy, through their own Weakneſs, and their own Imagination.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That there may be a true and impartial Information held forth to every one to whoſe Hands this Diſcourſe ſhall come, of the true Riſe, and Progreſs, of my Entrance into, and Separation from the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> in order to the ſilencing of thoſe falſe Aſperſions which have been caſt, not only upon me, but alſo upon the aforenamed People them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by reaſon of me: And which is more eſpecially upon the Truth it Self, which through miſrepreſentation, and miſunderſtanding of things, hath much ſuffered. Theſe things Conſidered, I hope it will be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by all ſober-minded Perſons, that I am in this Work, upon a great Duty, which I may not be at reſt, till it be effected: and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe herein, the Temptations and Wiles of Satan are Diſcovered, and in meaſure detected; which many being ignorant of, could not Believe, or Avoid: And although I muſt, and do expect, That there will be ſent forth Floods after me, even to the very drowning of me, (if poſſible) by Reproaches, Calumnies, Aſperſions, and whatever may be to render me, or make me Odious, (as divers have appeared in ſuch-like very active towards me already,) but thoſe who profeſs the higheſt Truth, even the Perfection, and abounds therein, dares not, nay, they cannot appear in the Language of the Beaſt, of the Serpent, of the Deceiver: yet how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever things be, I ſhall abide where I am; therefore I count not any thing which I may ſuffer valuable, in compariſon of that Peaee, I have in bearing this Witneſs, which is not anothers, but fulfilled in, and on my Perſon. So that I may truly ſay, (as in another Caſe) <hi>What I have heard with mine Ears, and ſeen with mine Eyes, and felt with my poor tormented Body and Spirit; That I have teſtified, and do teſtifie, and my Witneſs therein is true.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:118021:4"/>
               <head>To which, let me add a few Words by way of Caution to thee in the peruſal of what followeth.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> That thou Conſider what thou Readeſt, and underſtand things as they are: Alſo, be ſerious in thy Obſervation, and be not light in Mind, nor eaſily tickled with toyiſh Laughter at ſuch Vanities as thou mayeſt perceive to have attended me: But Watch and Pray, That thou alſo mayeſt not be led into Temptation. For I aſſure thee, That in the hour of my Temptation, I judged thoſe Madneſſes and Follies, great and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things, though now (through Mercy) I look upon them with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Eye.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Deſpiſe not the Scriptures, wherein the Minde of God is ſo preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and plentiouſly Recorded; neither doat too much upon them, for therein the Deceiver will work in thee Subtilly, to the drowning of thy Underſtanding, by forming in thee Imaginations and comprehenſions of things which are not, (I mean things which are not in the Counſel of God) by which the Unbelieving and Diſobedient Minde will be kept nouriſhed in thee; therefore be not wiſe above what is written either in the Scriptures or in thy Self, leſt the Light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> become a Rock of Offence, and a Stone of Stumbling unto thee; for both which were my Errors, by which I dearly ſuffered.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Watch unto Prayer, and be ſtaied in what is thy Obedience, that ſo thy Underſtanding might be opened, and thou mayest be able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between things that differ: as ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Try the Spirits whether they are of God:</hi> for there are, that have a great ſeeming-ſameneſs (at leaſt, a great ſimilitude and likeneſs of God) as when thou ſhalt be inwardly moved to Speak or Act: See that thou impute not that to God which is thine own, nor aſcribe not that to thy Self which is His; and by how much the more Difficult it is for thee to Diſtinguiſh thy own Spirit in its Operations and Effects, from the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations and Effects of the true and faithful Spirit of the Lord; be ſo much the more Humble and Lowly, and filled with Moderation, both towards thy Self, and others; until thou art Reſtored to a cleerer Sight.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Be not raſh in Judging nor Cenſuring; an Evil whereunto I my ſelf was moſt inveterately addicted, and is the univerſal Diſtemper of theſe times; for unſavoury Expreſſions being out of Charity, eſpecially
<pb facs="tcp:118021:5"/>where it come ſhort of Knowledge, ſtands not in the Counſel of God, though many glory therein; but they Acting from themſelves, and ſo their work being their own, true Judgement will reſt upon them: the wiſdom which is from above, being pure and peaceable, and full of gentleneſs; yea, even to the Froward (otherwiſe, I ſay, otherwiſe what had become of me, and others, this day?) but the Word of Truth will Rebuke in his day, when the Eyeſhall ſee as it is ſeen, beholding things as they are, and not as Fancied or Imagined to be.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> If thy Heart be ſet Free, pray for the Author, that he may be kept by the power of God in Obedience to that Faith which is Salvation, who referring thee to the Diſcourfe as it follows, bids thee <hi>Farewel.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>John Toldervy.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>WE whoſe Names are hereunto Subſcribed, being Certified of the Contents and Circumſtances of the Diſcourſe enſning; and ſome of us having Peruſed a Part, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the Whole of it, are fully ſatisfied of the Truth of Things Reported in it; and do Recommend it as a Piece worthy to be Read and taken into Conſideration by all ſerious Chriſtians, as a ſad and very remarkable Providence of God to be Obſerved of all thoſe who take pleaſure either in the knowledge of the gracious Works of God, or in the Diſcovery of the Wiles and Subtilties of the Devil; And as a ſeaſonable Warning-piece unto all others, that they be not taken in the like Snare: And if taken, that they may recover themſelves out.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Brooks</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Thomas Jacomb</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>George Cokayn</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Will. Adderley.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Goodwin</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Tombes</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Will. Jenkyn</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Matth. Poole.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118021:5"/>
            <head>The Foot out of the Snare.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>J. T.</hi> having for divers years been full of zeal after the things of God, by which zeal I was led forth with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding love after the knowledge of Chriſt: to which end, I ſought after thoſe Ways and Means which I was perſwaded to be moſt uſeful for the ſatisfying of my Judgment, &amp; clearing of my Conſcience, as Duties enjoyned, in order to my up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and cloſe walking with God, and blameleſs life and converſation amongſt men: To the ſame end, I was led forth, with much fervencie of ſpirit, after the Teachings of thoſe whom I judged to be moſt enlightned with that Spirit which was of God, and that were eſteemed of the primeſt Profeſſors, to be very knowing and underſtanding of what the truth, (or ſubſtance and life) was. To which end, I laboured, were it poſſible, (in that way,) to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what was pure, out of divers Opinions; that ſo one knowledg, one minde, witneſſed by one Truth (my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding being well informed) might act me to live in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with God, by a holy and innocent life.</p>
            <p>But after a time, in regard of much unſtableneſs I ſaw
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118021:6"/>in divers Teachers by the diverſity of their Opinions, and alſo much Confuſion in many Societies who made a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to be gathered together by one Spirit pure of God, into one pure minde, and ſo at unity with one pure God; it occaſioned much trouble and diſquietneſs in me. Whereupon, conſidering ſeriouſly with my ſelf, I ſought diligently what the cauſe ſhould be of all this diviſion, by which men profeſſing the Truth were thus diſtracted in their own mindes.</p>
            <p>Upon which, there was cleared to my underſtanding, Truth being but one, the miniſtration of righteouſneſs which proceedeth from this Truth, muſt neceſſarily be the ſame; therefore, that which occaſioned this Diviſion, was the wiſdom of the fleſh, which continually was, and ſtill is, at enmity with Truth; God being not the author of confuſion, but of peace.</p>
            <p>After this, I found a little pleaſure in hearing of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, becauſe of the pleaſantneſs of their diſcourſe, by the excellencie of their beautified language; but nothing ſufficient to edifie or learn me with knowledge: for in hearing I could not underſtand, in ſeeing I could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that any thing I ever ſaw or heard did proceed from a right underſtanding of the minde of God, there being ſo many mixtures by what I apprehended in every thing ſpoken forth by all.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, was I perſwaded to ſee what might be learned from others who were out of the way of theſe profeſſions: by whoſe Doctrine (together with what I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended of my ſelf) by the operation of a ſpirit infuſed into me, after a ſhort time, there was made clear to my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding what follows. But firſt, I ſhall declare the manner of my entrance into this belief.</p>
            <p>Being thus perſwaded, I began to be very inquiſitive af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome other people, that might accord with, and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118021:6"/>of good to me, whoſe life &amp; converſation might be one with their doctrine; both which being of God, might certainly confirm their unity with God.</p>
            <p>So in a ſhort time I became affected with thoſe people called by the name of Seekers: but afterwards hearing at a private houſe two of thoſe called by the name of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers; and much obſerving their diſcourſe, little was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but all tending to the deſtruction of every the leaſt ſin. So by the ſincerity of their diſcourſe, with the ſobriety of their appearance, I was taken ſomewhat affected with them: upon which, I was perſwaded to make a further enquiry after that Sect; though to my wiſdom, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what was ſpoke was againſt all ſin, yet there was nothing declared of the myſtery of the Goſpel of Chriſt. But upon a further enquiry in the obſervation of them, I ſaw their order, their maner of teaching, and duties; and found, as was declar'd by them, as far as I perceiv'd, that all ſpake the ſame things; their Miniſtery was one, all in one Order, united compleat in one Minde, whereby they were acted as one in their duties: whereupon, I concluded, that ſurely theſe people were of God, ſent forth as witneſſes for himſelf, againſt all others, who took the name of God in their mouthes, and declared themſelves to be the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, though they were made Miniſters of man, and ſent forth by man, whoſe Doctrine ſtood in the will of Man; and not underſtanding what the Word of life was, therefore uncapable of edifying the people; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſters of the Letter, and not of the Spirit. Now ſince it was written, that the people of God ſhould be of one ſoul and one minde; God alſo being one, and his Name one; and theſe people declaring to be the ſame, who did live much witneſſed by their humility, one pure life, alſo moved to ſpeak and act onely from a true and faithful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God manifeſted in them, by which they appeared
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118021:7"/>to be as Lights in the world, and all others, who were in a ſubjection unto divers Forms, in many things taking li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to themſelves, their lives appeared to be judges of them, as well as their outward declaration: yet in regard of much ſtrangeneſs that I apprehended in their way, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the extraordinary bold confidence they had in their judging, which gave no liberty for the juſtification of any beſides themſelves; I could not finde a ſufficient ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to comply with them.</p>
            <p>A ſhort time following, being at a private
<note n="*" place="margin">Of thoſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Seekers.</note> Meeting, where after ſome time ſpent by two or three, who were making enquiry what ſhould be the meaning of the Spirit of God in two Scriptures, which ſeemingly did appear to contradict each other; there comes into the Meeting divers ſtrange men; and in the midſt of their diſcourſe upon thoſe Scriptures, there ſtood up a man of theſe ſtrangers; and ſilencing of them, he began with an exceeding bold courage to ſpeak, crying aloud, in theſe words, or to this effect, <hi>Praiſes, praiſes be to the Lord God for ever, who hath hid theſe things from the wiſe &amp; prudent, and hath revealed them unto babes:</hi> giving them to know, that the dark clouds were veiled over the Sun, and with this darkneſs did they go about to comprehend the light; but the light did ſee the darkneſs, and the darkneſs comprehended it not. So repeating over thoſe Scriptures, he affirmed with confidence, that they meant that they ſpake; and made thoſe plain to the underſtanding of many; affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thoſe who never came to live obedient to the Life which was of God in them, ſhould never come to ſee what was meant by the holy Spirit, which moved thoſe who lived the life of God to ſpeak them forth: the words of the Wiſe were dark to ſuch, who, by their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, had loſt their light. So Man having now loſt his guide, being blind, he ſeeks after Knowledge, by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118021:7"/>the teachings of that minde which is darkned; and ſo feeds upon that tree forbidden, of the knowledge of Good and Evil, not diſcerning: and beginning in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> he paſſed thorow the whole ſcope of the Scriptures, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring what was meant by them; and all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing turned by him into Allegories, typifying or figuring forth what was to be fulfilled in man, before he came to be born of the Spirit, the ſecond birth, without which there was no entrance into the Kingdom of God, (hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) which was in man, according to that Scripture, <hi>I will dwell in them, and walk in them: they ſhall be my people, and I will be their God.</hi> And ſo declaring what was meant by the firſt Adam, what by the ſecond Adam; what the Fall was, what the cauſe of the Fall; what reigned after the Fall, what by Redemption out of this fallen eſtate; the way of this Redemption; the effects produced in the way; the Inſtruments by whom this Redemption was to be wrought; how it was to be done, and where, which was in the man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo, that the Scripture was not the Word of God, but it was what was ſpoken from the Word: by the Word was meant Life; and the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures were a Declaration from this Word of Life: the Word was the ſubſtance from whence it was ſpoken; and this ſubſtance, the Word of Life, was the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God manifeſted in man, the gift of the Holy Spirit manifeſted in fleſh, made known in all, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might be guided to profit in that obedience re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of God; alſo, by which all the diſorder in the Creation of man, made by the flouds poured forth in man in that time of God's diſpleaſure, occaſioned by his fall from God into the Luſt, was to be put into the ſame order they were at the firſt, which was good: by which Word, the mountains were to be leveled, all hills were to be caſt down, and the valleys were to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118021:8"/>crooked places were to be made ſtrait, and rough wayes to be made ſmooth: every thing was to ſtand in awe before him; the lofty minde was to be pulled down, and all high thoughts and imaginations were to be burned up: and theſe things being not done by the Word in you, the pure Witneſſes of God lie ſlain in your ſtreets, the houſe of darkneſs, the houſe of bondage, thoſe Cities which ſpiritually have a relation to Sodom and Egypt: and I was ſent by God to declare againſt that in you, by which you are blinded, and ſo the Witneſſes kept ſlain: expreſſing with a firm confidence, that ſearching of the Scripture was not the way to finde out the knowledge of Chriſt; but the turning the minde to within, there to be taught by the meaſure of God, the Law written in the heart: and ſo ſtanding in obedience to it, in time death being paſſed over all that ſinned, Chriſt would be brought forth; which ſin reigned from <hi>Adam</hi> till <hi>Moſes,</hi> even over all that had not ſinned after the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of <hi>Adam</hi>'s tranſgreſſion; <hi>Adam</hi> the earthly nature in man, which prevailed with him to be earthly minded, to love the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs: which death reigned over the whole man, till <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſervant of God, which gave the Law to the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the ſeed of the Faithful; by which they were to be guided to the Angel of the Covenant, Chriſt, and ſo witneſs the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which to know, ſaith God, is life; vvhich life was manifeſted in him, and he ſavv it the onely Begotten of God: and from vvhat he had ſeen, felt, heard, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in himſelf, that vve alſo might have fellovvſhip, did he declare theſe things: concluding with a ſtrict Charge, in the Name of the living God, that we turn to him, the Rock whence we were hewn, as we reſpected our eternal peace: bearing record, that he, the God of life, ſtood waiting ready to receive all that turn to him, and having
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118021:8"/>your faces Sion-ward, go on bearing your Croſſes joyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for his reward is with him, and his work before him.</p>
            <p>So after about an hours diſcourſe in things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, all ſpoken with a firm confidence, mighty power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully declared, with ſo much ſcriouſneſs that poſſible could be, ſuppoſed to be far beyond whatever I ſaw by any man; and uſing thoſe words, Thee and Thou; barren of any Complement, or whatever might be taken in them to pleaſe man, they departed.</p>
            <p>Now upon the conſideration of divers things, alſo the ſtrong Ingagement laid upon us, as we tendered our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs, together with that bold undaunted confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he had in the Truth of what was ſpoken: all my former Knowledge, my former Belief, my former Hope, (being ſtruck with a great Fear) was immediately daſhed in pieces, they being taken to be earthen Veſſels, made by the Wiſdom which was begotten of the
<note n="*" place="margin">Self for the juſtifying of Self.</note> earthly Man; and then coming to underſtand that they were of thoſe People called by the name of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, together with what formerly I knew of them, I became ſtrongly affected with them: divers alſo of the ſame Meeting at the ſame time, being poſſeſs'd with the like perſwaſions.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, much love acted me to follow them very zealouſly; but in order to a more perfect clearing of my underſtanding, I remained a time before I complied with them, or made my ſelf known to any one of them: in which time, meeting with one whom I formerly knew to be a very ſerious true-hearted Man, who was converted to their Belief, and alſo ſubjected to their Obedience, who gave me to underſtand, that they were ſent forth to preach the Goſpel by the ſame Chriſt that the Apoſtles were; and, that the Perſon, that Son of God which died at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> was not the Redeemer of Man from Sin;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118021:9"/>but the Redeemer was in every particular Man, that Light by which he was given to ſee Sin, and enabled by it, if obeyed, to be redeemed from Sin: which Chriſt had redeemed them perfect, and now lived in them Lord of all things, by which they were made the Sons of God; and ſo what was manifeſted unto them by that ſubſtance, from that ſubſtance were they moved to ſpeak, which was the ſame Holy Ghoſt, by which the Apoſtles were endued, ſent forth, &amp; enabled to preach the Goſpel: and declaring of them much to admiration, how that ſometimes in the night they were immediately commanded by the eternal Spirit to go forth and preach the Goſpel, alſo by the like command, ſome of them were limited to faſt from Food (as I remember) about twenty or more dayes together
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>And afterwards I knew ſome who fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted</hi> 30 <hi>or</hi> 40 <hi>days.</hi>
               </note>; which was intended to make them willing and pliable to the will of God in the travel of their Spirit, before they came to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the reſt of the new created Being or Work of God in them. So he gave me to underſtand the next day of their meeting, and the place where, with earneſt invitation to be there.</p>
            <p>Now that I might have the Counſel of God in what I did, as touching my uniting with them, when I came home I went to Prayers; and being mightily carried forth in that Duty, very often before the time of their meeting, I looked upon it as a ſign which did make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the good pleaſure of God in my cloſing with them: ſo at that meeting, three of the chiefeſt of them being Speakers, whoſe matter and manner of preaching was more taking unto me than all the former, but eſpecially the powerful operation of their Prayer, all which effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually wrought upon me: whereupon, my minde being eſtabliſhed, I was moved to make a confeſſion of my ſelf, concluding, with the owning of them in the preſence of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118021:9"/>all the people: upon which, I became ſubject to the teachings of a Spirit in my ſelf, (the which being believed to be the Chriſt of God, the Redeemer from ſin) I was fully perſwaded, that if denying any thing in the leaſt that it required, I could not be redeemed; and ſince that the Truth was made manifeſt, if diſobeyed, no remedy, I ſhould be eternally damned.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, as I reſpected my Salvation, this Redeemer was to work me, and to diſpoſe of me according to his will; and whatever I willed, was not to be done, but to be croſſed by my being ſubject to this Redeemer. Upon which, there aroſe a great Controverſie in my Spirit, of what ſtood in the will of man, and what did not: ſaid one Spirit, This is in the will, when it was not: on the contrary ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Spirit, (as to the ſame thing) this is not in the will: and ſo through fear I ſhould always yield a ſubjection un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Spirit by which I was limited and brought under bondage to do many things in my will againſt my will: whereupon I became a deſtroyer of the will of God, as touching that Liberty which was allowed me in the uſe of my Members either to ſpeak or to act; alſo in the uſe of thoſe Creatures made for the ſervice of Man; and ſo as thoſe former weakneſſes which reigned in me through the darkneſs of my underſtanding, came to be deſtroyed, my underſtanding, being not then well enlighened, greater weakneſſes (as to the not enjoyment of my ſelf) did ariſe; alſo as one imaginary being in me came to be overthrown, there was begotten the like Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in another ſhape, and by it was I wrought upon to believe many things, (by me undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) and alſo led forth, and acted from one thing unto another, according to what followeth:</p>
            <p>So believing that what was manifeſted of God in man, was the Light of Life which was one with himſelf, as it is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118021:10"/>written, <hi>I and my Father are one:</hi> by which was given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Man a ſavory diſcerning of what was Good and what was Evil, what was darkneſſe, which darkneſſe was to be expelled by this light, there remained therefore no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the Man to do, but to ſtand in the Will of that which was pure in him, and ſo by it he became a Judge of what impurity or the Law of Sin would act him in, which ſin, the occaſion of Death, was to be ſwallowed up in victory, that ſo only the light of life which is inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, might live; there being nothing in Man for Death: even as a King, over-ruling all in ſubjection unto himſelf.</p>
            <p>Whereupon was concluded, that Man was the Cauſe of all this diſtraction and confuſion in himſelf, and ſo abſtracted from this confuſion, was that being which made an appearance of holineſſe in the minds of all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed religious People, ſubjected under divers Forms, Ordinances and Ceremonies, which is a vapour it ſelf, and muſt die, as the Ordinances were ſhaddows and are ceaſed: but Man having loſt the kernel, the ſubſtance which giveth nouriſhment and ſatisfies, he feedeth upon the dry husk, and being not refreſhed with the true Bread and Water of Life, he remaineth alwaies ſeeking, and never comes to know what is true; alwaies feeding and never ſatisfied until he comes to underſtand where the Bread of Life is to be found, which is in himſelf, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it is written, <hi>I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one:</hi> and ſo eternal life living in us, there needs no more thirſt, there needs no more hunger after Knowledge: <hi>this is eternal life, to know God and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince there is much Myſterie recorded in Scripture, it is concluded, that the knowledge of thoſe Myſteries is to know the Will of Chriſt, and ſo the way to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118021:10"/>yea, it is believed, that the knowledge of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, is to know God and Chriſt: though it is ſpoken concerning Chriſt, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life:</hi> And again it is written, <hi>the Word is nigh you, in the mouth, and in the heart;</hi> ſo that the Way, the Truth, and the Life is in us: that which giveth Salvation. But ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">Judas<hi>'s love being removed from Christ by the ſeducements of the Deceiver, his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding became loſt, and ſo his minde was driven out from God into the Earth.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Judas, How is it that thou wilt manifeſt thy ſelf unto us, and not unto the World?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Concluſion alſo, proceeds from the evil one transformed in Man, he being ſcattered, very confuſed, and darkned in his underſtanding, covered as with a vail; and ſo Satan, as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of Light, moveth and leadeth forth to divers Duties, which are his own, for the upholding of his Reign in Man. Alſo feeds Man with Wiſdom and variety of pleaſant Language, called Gifts, in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances for the upholding of his Duties: by which ſin being ſhaded over, he is juſtified; many being called failings; but perfection is not to be attained in this life, but in another life (hereafter:) though it is written, <hi>Except Chriſt be in you, ye are Reprobates.</hi> having rent the garments of righteouſneſs, ye are acurſed, being hipped up above the Truth, and trampling the Blood of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the life of the Innocent in the duſt: ſo that if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and Finiſher of our Faith be living in us, there is perfection; but if not, perfection is not, faithfulneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ceaſed.</p>
            <p>Now the World was underſtood to be the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> in which Man was placed at the firſt, and ſtill is; and the Trees of this Garden all living beings, proceeding out of the Earth, living in and upon the Earth; all which having their being of God, the life of all things, by ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of himſelf, that proceedeth forth of the Earth,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118021:11"/>God the Life, who created all the Life, from whence is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the increaſe of all.</p>
            <p>It was alſo underſtood that Paradiſe was in Man, where his delight ſhould be, where his minde ſhould be ſtayed at unity with God, who made choice to take up his Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and abode there himſelf, with his increaſe, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of Love, and beloved Ones, who were to be kept, nouriſhed, and refreſhed by Man 's living obedient unto the will of God in the ſame ſimplicity of Love, and ſo at unity with this Family of Love, the Seed of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then was this underſtood to be the ſtate in which all men were created, and is now alſo the cauſe of his fall.</p>
            <p>All men were made of nothing, and ſtill are; as one Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration paſſeth away, another Generation ſucceedeth, by God the Author of all: and ſo, as one increaſe by him was brought to their end, another increaſe was produced forth of himſelf, according as it is written, <hi>I kill, and I make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore in the firſt Creation of Men, they were made pure and holy, without ſin, in the likeneſs of that God, who was their Maker, perfect; for where no ſin was, there was perfection.</p>
            <p>But Man, when he came into a growth in the World, he ſaw the excellency of that Proviſion (of that Fruit) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared of God to be a nouriſhment (or refreſhment) for him; he began of himſelf, by hearkening to the weaker (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him the fleſhly minde) to be diſcontented with that allowance which was ſufficient for his uſe, and pleaſe the Creature himſelf, rather than God that made him, and by whom he lived; which Nature, reſpected himſelf beyond that pure Nature which is of God, given in to him, by which the Creation of God was to be preſerved in its or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, according as it is written, in the Church of God, <hi>The head of the woman is the man, the head of the man is Chriſt, the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118021:11"/>head of Chriſt is God:</hi> Which Church is in Man, as it is written, <hi>Ye are the Temples of the living God.</hi> Now the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man being the ſillieſt and weakeſt part, alſo that which deſireth moſt to be dallying with ſuch things in which it might take delight, leſt ſhe ſhould defile her ſelf, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour her head the man, by alluring of him to commit Fornication with her; ſhe is to be kept in ſubjection by him, as he is taught by the Word; which Word Chriſt, the Light of Life, is given to declare what the will of God is; but man, having given way to the weaker being, ſhe is become the Head and Ruler of all: it was pleaſant, and ſhe deſired, and that cauſed the Man to taſte; for he willed, and that cauſed the Sun to be darkned; his light, which was given to diſcover the will of God, to be clouded by the begotten will of man, yielding ſubjection to weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Now the Sun being darkned, could not anſwer the end for which it was given: ſo the will of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came loſt by, and unknown to man; he having created to himſelf an Image, falls down, and worſhips it, by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual ſlavery to the things of this world, ſerving divers Gods and divers Lords, by which he hath brought himſelf under the curſe of God, having ſlain the witneſſes that were given in him from God. Wherefore, at the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection the Book of Conſcience ſhould be opened, out of which the witneſſes ſhould be raiſed to life, and ſo man by whom they were ſlain, ſhould by them receive condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; but ſuch who bare teſtimony of the firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which is man being ſubjected unto that which ſhewed him any ſin, the true and faithful witneſſes would be raiſed to life, by which he might ſee the leaſt ſin; and they ruling in him here, ſhould be the juſtifier of him hereafter, the ſecond death having no power.</p>
            <p>Again, it was further underſtood, that man, in his own will, by his own wiſdom, his minde being driven out into
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118021:12"/>the Earth, forth of Paradiſe into ſlavery, by the flaming Swords of thoſe Spirits ſent from God, ſeeking after Knowledge, begets in himſelf Children of Fornication, from whence proceedeth divers Languages; <hi>Babylon</hi> being built up in him, by which confuſion he is acted to do thoſe Services required by the Whoriſh Woman, that well-favoured and beautified Harlot, whoſe Ornaments appeared glorious, and beſpangled with thoſe Jewels that had the greateſt Gliſter, whoſe brightneſs was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent for Purity, by which they appeared excellent to all the ſpectators: All which, being but as a gilded Picture without ſubſtance; even as Wind, carrying the minds of men to and fro by their airy imagination; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them to believe that it is the Spirit of God, though abſtracted from the diverſity of Languages, proceeding from thoſe Beings, or Children of Fornication begotten in him by himſelf, through the Allurements of the Whoriſh woman. So man being thus darkned in his underſtanding, what is fancied (or ſuppoſed) to be true by that which deſireth Knowledge in him, becauſe he hath loſt his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory diſcerning, he buildeth upon it as confident, and ſo the weakneſs in him, and his own imagination, is judged by him to be the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>Now man being exalted into ſuch a high degree by the pride of his own heart, and not reſting contented in that place which he was Created in by God, he thereby brought Condemnation upon himſelf; and this was done by every particular man, being acted by, and made ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to, thoſe things, which he was made by right of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Lord of.</p>
            <p>Here man being led forth in a ſubjection to vanity, his Food is a vapour or duſt not able to keep life, therefore no remedy; having corrupted himſelf, with an incurable Diſeaſe, he muſt die, he muſt die: except by a ſubjection
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118021:12"/>to the teachings of that Law written in the heart, Chriſt be raiſed from the dead, there to live and reign in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and true Judgement, as at the beginning; and ſo having purchaſed an everlaſting inheritance through a perfect Obedience, there is no death of that poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>I Shall now declare divers of thoſe effects which this Change wrought in, and upon me: At my firſt entrance into this way, before I came to a right underſtanding of what was true.</p>
            <p>Said they, <q>Having owned the Truth, ye need not that Man teach you any more: if you never ſee our faces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, there is that in you by which you may be taught.</q> Which was taken to be the Life, the holy Seed of God raiſed out of Death by that which was ſpoken from the Life in them.</p>
            <p>So immediately in the Obſervation of them, though confidently ſuppoſed it was by a Command from the Life in me, I became ſubjected to divers Ceremonies: As, not to Maſter any man: Not to pull off the Hat to any man: Not to ſpeak the word You, but inſtead thereof, Thee and Thou: Not to uſe any Complements or Greetings to any; believing, That Bowing to a man, was a Worſhipping of him: Not to direct my Minde in Drinking to any, as familiarly is uſed amongſt Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo, by the ſame perſwaſion was I wrought upon to pull off thoſe Points I wore at my Knees, my Bandſtrings, Hatband, Buttons that I judged were unneceſſary on my Coat; ſome of which I brake to pieces, and threw away; others I made a ſpeedy diſpoſal of, with many other things; burned divers Books that were Divinity, judging that they were what was ſpoken from the teachings of the Devil in thoſe that write them; ſome made away; others brake in pieces and threw away. Having a buſineſs in my Charge,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118021:13"/>the Redeeming part of an Eſtate for my Mother, lately loſt by the death of my Father, which thing was very fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceeded in, and very poſſibly in a ſhort to have been effected, amongſt other of thoſe ſeduced perſwaſions, which ſubtilly, under a pretence of ſelf-denial, accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed its ends upon me, I was engaged &amp; effectually prevailed upon, utterly to withdraw from this buſineſs; by which now my Mother and many little ones, lieth much under the ſufferings of my deſerted obedience: but the workings of this power was ſo predominant upon my Spirit, that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the leaſt acknowledgement, much leſs performance of duty to any. Now</p>
            <p>In my former proſecuting of this buſineſs, having diſpoſed of what Moneys I was provided with, for the charges of my proceedings, and being neceſſarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, I adventured (though unwarrantably) for my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſupply, without conſent, to take the ſum of 40 <hi>s.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me, in caſe I ſhould have had occaſion to make uſe thereof, before I received any return from my Relations, being far diſtant from <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But a ſhort inſtant following, being perſwaded in this way, as I was reſtrained from proceeding in this buſineſs, ſo alſo I was engaged to make known what I had done; otherwiſe than I intended (which was privily to reſtore it as I had taken it forth) which I did; reſtoring the ſame which I had received, not having made any uſe thereof.</p>
            <p>Now amongſt other things which this change of minde wrought in and upon me, and by which firſt I became famous in the general diſcourſe of men, eſpecially amongſt thoſe of whom I was known, this buſineſs was a chief; by which, through the not underſtanding of the thing, divers concluſions have been conceived, otherwiſe than the Truth; by which, many abuſive reproaches have been unjuſtly caſt upon me: but what I ſpeak, cannot
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118021:13"/>in the leaſt be gain-ſaid, known unto thoſe whom it did concern.</p>
            <p>A ſhort time after my compliance with that Spirit which entred in me by the obſervation of their practice declared to be from the teachings of the Spirit, Chriſt in them; My Maſter having been at the Wells, came home; ſo out of that reſpect I had to what was good in him, and alſo that love I bare towards his eternal reſt with God, I was moved to go to him preſently, and inform him of my Reſtoration from the depth of thoſe deluſions, which I was ſerviceable in, by the miniſtery of thoſe Teachers, who were blinded in their underſtanding, not knowing the myſtery of godlineſs: upon which, I really ſuppoſed that he would have been prevailed upon by me to frequent our Meetings, that if may be the ſame Miniſtery ſpoken from the Life, by which the Life was raiſed in me, might effect the ſame end in him, unto his Salvation; ſo coming to him, I wrote a Scroll, took him by the Arm or Cloak, and bade him Sit down <hi>William Web;</hi> not bowing, not pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling off the hat, not Maſter, for then I denied that title to him, though related to him a Servant, as afterwards I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied all relations, from the words of one, He that liveth in the Light will ſee no difference: after which, I ſpake theſe words, <hi>How does thy body do?</hi> for, as may be obſerved, we made a ſeparation between the Body and the Spirit. Now the obſervation of my carriage, with the ſtrangeneſs of that expreſſion <hi>Body,</hi> moved him to ſpeak theſe words: <hi>John, what is the matter? where is the Servant's Obedience? where is the Maſter's honour?</hi> The anſwer (as I remember) was thus: 'My Maſter was the faithful Spirit in me. So I gave him to underſtand, <q>That I had heard the Miniſters of the everlaſting Goſpel, by whom I was converted to the faithful obedience, by which I ſhould finde Life; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring of him (as he reſpected his eternal happineſs) to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118021:14"/>come amongſt us, that ſo, what is true might be made manifeſt to, and in him: For (ſaid I) from the Lord do I declare, that all the Miniſters of theſe times (or that were not of us) are the Miniſters of the Devil; and in particular, <hi>Feak,</hi> that Miniſter, whom he heard, was of the Devil, whoſe Miniſtery was Death.</q> So being ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, by much diſlike in him of what was ſpoken, I was diſmiſſed by him at that time.</p>
            <p>A while after this, when he and his Company were at Dinner, I was moved by that Spirit in me, to go and Dine w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> them: now becauſe it was againſt my will, I concluded that this moving was indeed from the Lord; which ſervice was intended by the Lord, to make known unto him, that he willed there ſhould be no Difference between Man and Man: So I went into the Room where he was, took me a Stool, and ſate down at the Head of the Table; which being done, I applied my Minde to my Buſineſs. Then was asked me ſome Queſtions forth of the Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Duty of the Servant, which was Anſwered in the juſtifying of my ſelf, as to that Deed: giving him to know, That I was the Servant of the living God, and he was not; therefore I had more right unto the Greatures than he had: So having finiſhed my work, I departed.</p>
            <p>Now I was, with exceeding love, out of reſpect unto my eternal Salvation, formerly fixed with a reſolution to be taught by the Light in me, and ſo never to ſin any more; upon which I became very punctual in every word and every Deed: Alſo, having received a ſtrict Charge, with the reſt, That nothing ſhould be Spoken or Acted, but what might be eternally witneſſed; whereupon, when any Cuſtomers came to deal with me, I durſt not ask them, What they wanted? believing that thoſe Words could not be eternally witneſſed; for they knew what they came for: Then when that was required which they came
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118021:14"/>for, I durſt not make in the price of it but one word; and if by them tempted to more, becauſe of what was expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of advantage to themſelves by a cheaper Rate, I ſhould be provoked to look ſternly, with wrath and envie, out of the extream hatred I bare towards that Spirit which moved them to ſpeak more than was needful: and ſo by this, and that Spirit by which I was limited to thoſe words, Thee, and Thou, and not pulling off my Hat, without any civil reſpect in my Carriage, I was made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for that Service, by which was intended a way for my livelihood. Alſo, divers of thoſe Commodities we dealt in, having honourable Names, and other having ſuch Names which I judged were not meet; I was commanded and enjoyned by this Spirit in me, to give unto them freſh Names, believing that thoſe Names did proceed from the invention of Man, and they ſtood in the Fall, as did every thing that was invented and made by Man, and ſo uſed by Man, that was not abſolute neceſſary: Alſo, it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that all thoſe things before ſpoken of which I was limited from, ſtood in the will of Man, and they came in the Fall.</p>
            <p>I was farther perſwaded not to eate any thing that I loved, believing, that what did ſet a Difference of any Creature, ſtood in the Will; for he looked upon all things, and behold it was good; therefore it was of Man that gave a reſpect to any thing above other; ſo by degrees at the laſt, I was wrought upon to eat nothing but Crums, pickings of Bones, when finiſhed by others; with ſuch Food that was deſtructive to my health, it being contrary to pure Nature: Alſo, I was limited from eating of the Creature what was needful to the ſatisfying of Nature, ſo that I was made extream poor, &amp; ſo changed, as though I were not the ſame man; faſting ſome weeks from eating little more than Nature would have required to eat in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118021:15"/>one day. Going along Cheap-ſide, I ſaw Cabbage-ſtocks, with broken leaves of Colworts, which were thrown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by the Market-women: at which ſight I was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by a command of this Spirit in me, to gather them all up, and carry them home; which being done, I was commanded in the like nature, to dreſs them, and the next food I did eat, to eat them.</p>
            <p>The ſtrangeneſs of this alteration being ſo great, divers Friends came to ſee me, intending by diſcourſe, to work me to a conſideration of my condition, by a better inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my underſtanding; but Reaſon being deſtroyed, nothing took place in me, but I judged them to be in the dark; and, that what was ſpoken from them was fleſh, their mindes and underſtandings being alienated from the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> my Maſter alſo, with his Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and others of the Family, when diſcourſing with me, all what was ſpoken by them was judged to be from the evil one in them, whoſe I believed they were.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Now (ſaid they) coming to live the life of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, you will finde the meaning of them, they being fulfilled by you, to be opened to your underſtanding by the life in you, and ſo they will be found another thing than what formerly they were;</q> but at this time, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received that knowledge that I was to wait for, the birth, ſuch a time, out of my own wiſdom, my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and imagination, going to read the Scriptures, I found ſuch a ſtrange alteration in many things, contrary to what formerly I did believe, that I was taken affected with it: upon which I was perſwaded to read over the whole Scriptures; and in reading, that which deſired knowledge in me, prevailed upon me to ſearch out the meaning of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things; which ſeeking deſtroyed my former under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and gave me to believe another meaning: then did I really conclude, That I was taught by the word in me,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118021:15"/>the ſame word which the holy men of God, that ſpake forth the Scriptures had living in them, by which they were inabled to ſpeak them forth; upon which I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by a ſtronger phanſie, ſuppoſed to be the Spirit of Chriſt, to ſpend all my time, that poſſible I could gain, night and day, to learn knowledge by the teachings of the Holy Ghoſt in me: by which in a ſhort time I did really believe, that there was not any thing expreſſed, but I had the perfect knowledge of: in the end, words and letter did ſignifie to my apprehenſion divers meanings. Thus fancy and imagination acting together, I was beſotted, and made perfect drunk in my underſtanding, by the airy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit gotten in from without, by which I became like unto a diſtracted man.</p>
            <p>Having this perſwaſion in my ſelf, that all knowledge contained in the Scriptures was revealed unto me, I was really poſſeſſed with a confident belief, that Chriſt Jeſus that died at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was a figure of me, and that I was the true Chriſt, that Angel ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> which was to flie through the midſt of Heaven, declaring the everlaſting Goſpel to all Kindreds, Nations, Tongues, and People.</p>
            <p>There was alſo revealed unto me by the teachings of that Spirit in me, which gave me the knowledge of the Scriptures, that the diſſolution of all things would be at the end of ſixty three yeers; in which time, by my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and the reſt of our Teachers, the Jews were to be called, with the Gentiles, who had loſt the knowledge of the Goſpel immediately after the Apoſtles dayes, from which time until now, that God raiſed his Spirit to Life in thoſe of us, both Jews and Gentiles have lain in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſerving the God of the World, the Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and without the knowledge of the true God in the world. Wherefore all, both Miniſters and people, that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118021:16"/>were ſince a ſhort time after the Apoſtles dayes, they having bowed down to the Gods of the Earth, and ſo worſhipped the Gods of the Heathen; the God of Gods, who is the Lord of all, had condemned them, and their gods eternally: Wherefore now the Candle of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed was to be put out, by the everlaſting Goſpel, ſpoken from the eternal Life in us; by which, thoſe that were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to Salvation, ſhould have the Life raiſed in them, whoſe brightneſs, as it was revealed, ſhould ſwallow up all that was for Condemnation; ſo the eternal Life living in them, there was Salvation.</p>
            <p>It was alſo believed, That I ſhould live to the End, and then Chriſt, which died at Jeruſalem, was to meet me in the Mount of God, which was in a multitude of bright Clouds, where I was immediately to be transformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Celeſtial Body, all Spirit; where that Chriſt and I ſhould ſit Judges of all that ever had a Being in the World.</p>
            <p>Wherefore now, it being ſo, that I was to be the Miniſter in the hand of God, for the converting of thoſe who were Elected to Salvation, to the true knowledge, by which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life was to be found; my minde was informed, that though I had the perfect knowledge of the Scripture, it was not ſufficient for this work: And, alſo I was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, There was a greater Revelation to be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in me, than there was in Chriſt, or the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I was enjoyned, that I ſhould ſpend all the time that poſſibly I could, in waiting for Revelations from Heaven: which I did, according to the teachings of this Spirit in me; hearkening diligently, with my minde fixed upwards towards Heaven, in expectation to hear ſome voyce from thence: Whereupon, the firſt time I really ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed I heard many excellent voyces, which made an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſweet, and pleaſant Melody: Upon which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118021:16"/>they were Spirits ſent from God, to make known unto me, the greatneſs of that joy there was in Heaven be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of me; by which appearance, being over-raviſhed, I was firmly reſolved to be pliable to that Spirit which moved me in this way of waiting.</p>
            <p>So a ſhort time following, there appeared to me two Spirits in the likeneſs of a Man's ſhade; which appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were believed to be Angels ſent from God to miniſter unto me; from whom did proceed, to my acceptation, at that time, excellent things concerning God, and Chriſt that died at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> alſo concerning the Angels, and the excellency of that place called Heaven.</p>
            <p>Following this, there came many ſuch-like Spirits that were all taken to be Angels; at which ſight, there was a voice ſpake in me, which gave greetings to thoſe appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; upon which, there was anſwered by them, <q>That within twenty five dayes, perfection ſhould be ſtabliſhed in me, and ſo I ſhould be made perfect, entire, wanting nothing, the whole work of God having been made manifeſt; then ſhould I ſuffer the likeneſs of that Death and Reſurrection, which was real by him that died at <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> after which, I ſhould be ſent forth to preach the Goſpel; and then <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel ſhould be living in me, by whom I ſhould be carried to and fro, throughout the World, and enabled to preach the Goſpel.</q>
            </p>
            <p>After this time, for theſe twenty five dayes, when the Spirit in me willed me to go private, which was ſometimes in the day, and almoſt all theſe twenty five nights, I durſt not deny the movings, as I reſpected my Salvation; yea, I do verily believe I did not reſt one night with another, above one hour in a night, all the time of theſe twenty five dayes; moſt of which time, I had the company of theſe appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, according as I was moved to deſire them by that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118021:17"/>which was in me: for when I was moved by that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to deſire them, they would come: and when that mov'd me to require their departure, they would depart: and conſtantly when they came, they brought with them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Muſicks, which alwayes kept over my head, and followed me according as I moved: the apparitions making merry amongſt themſelves, dancing, leaping and flying about the room, according to the muſicks of thoſe Spirits which continually plaid over my head.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now declare ſome things that were acted by my orderly ſubjection to the teachings of this Spirit in me, and thoſe apparitions in the time of theſe twenty five dayes.</p>
            <p>There was not a day or night, but many ſtrange actions were performed; but I ſhall ſpeak of ſome few, by which may be judged what the reſt were.</p>
            <p>The ſecond or third night I was commanded by that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in me, to ſtay up all night: ſo about mid-night, five of theſe apparitions, with thoſe Spirits which made ſuch pleaſant melody came, as I was waiting for revelations: one of which Spirits (as they were flying about the room) came and overſhadowed my face, as though a vail, and ſpake to me, telling me in my ear, <q>That three of the ſeven plagues had been poured forth upon me; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of my diligent obedience in all things required by the Spirit in me, two were not, and the other two were yet to come; and, that after my reſurrection from the dead, I ſhould make choice of twelve that were chiefeſt Speakers amongſt us, to be my Apoſtles: ſo parting from me, they went all to dancing.</q> About an hour after, as I was ſtanding before the fire, I heard ſomthing that made a noiſe: upon which I heard a voice ſpeak in me, ſaying, <hi>Babylon is fallen, Babylon is fallen;</hi> which was ſignificant to my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that all in me which formerly reign'd, was thrown
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118021:17"/>down, being daſhed in pieces by the coming of Chriſt; and turning round, I ſaw that the fire being much burned, fell down: then being weary of ſtanding, (having not ſate that night) I went to ſit down; &amp; going to ſit, I was commanded by one of theſe Spirts that I ſhould ſtand, for God was then preſent in the room. Whereupon, after about an hours ſtanding, looking for a revelation, I was over-ſhadowed as before like as with a vail, and commanded from a voice, immediately to pull off my ſhoes off my Feet, for the place where I ſtood was holy ground: and as God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Buſh, ſo God appeared now unto me in this revelation, giving me to underſtand, That the appearance of God unto <hi>Moſes</hi> was a figure of this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance unto me. Whereupon, I pulled off my ſhooes; and being ſtruck with an exceeding fear, much trembling, I pulled off my hat alſo, and laid it down: at which time, I was ſenſible of very much cold, it being an exceeding cold night: ſo immediately there came an extream warmth all over the room, and thence it ſeiſed upon my Feet, and with a tingling heat it raiſed it ſelf upwards, till over my Legs, and there reſted a little time, infuſing a heat into my legs; then did it ariſe by degrees, little and little, until at laſt my whole Body was encompaſſed with warmth, as though a great heat had been infuſed in me by a violent compulſion. All which time, I trembled ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, but durſt not move from that place I ſtood in. Alſo the tunes of the Spirits were changed into a great ſinging or hiſſing, much like to the noiſe of thouſands of Bees; and the apparitions danced: ſo a voice ſpake, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me by my name, telling me, <q>That I was <hi>John</hi> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of himſelf, as <hi>Iohn</hi> was the beloved of Chriſt; and he, that <hi>Iohn,</hi> was a figure of me.</q> So after ſome time ſpent, I could not contain, but ſpeak of my own accord theſe words, <hi>Ye are the Angels of the living God:</hi> concluding
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118021:18"/>with the owning of what was by them revealed. But in the ſpeaking of theſe Words, I ſtammered, out of fear: upon which, there flew one of theſe apparitions by me, and told me, <hi>That I had blaſphemed.</hi> What the cauſe was, I could not tell; but I ſuppoſed it to be, becauſe I ſpake theſe words in my own will, before I had a true moving from that Being in me: for I believed, that in doing of any deed, or ſpeaking of any word that ſtood in my own will, I did blaſpheme; judging, That what ſpake, moved, or acted in man, that had not a patient working, with a joynt concurrence of the whole man, was wrought in the will, and ſo imperfect, a blaſt which periſheth in its act, and ſo eternally not to be witneſſed; by which the whole man is defiled. Upon which, all the Spirits and the pleaſant noiſe vaniſhed away, and were not; alſo, the warmth infuſed in me, and encompaſſed about me, was taken away in the ſame nature as it came. Then was I ſtruck with a great fear, not knowing what this meant: upon which, as my manner was, when committing of any offence, as I was moved by the Spirit in me, I lay down upon the ground, with my face cloſe to the floor, which was believed to be the greateſt humility I could expreſs: and after a ſhort time of my wallowing and tumbling upon the ground, I was moved by that Spirit in me to lie ſtill on my belly with my face flat on the ground; which being done, immediately came the like warmth on the floor under me, as before; and from thence aroſe a great ſteam, which encompaſſed me over, and then ſeiſed upon me as before, infuſing a heat through my whole body: then was I by that Spirit in me moved to riſe up; but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it was not a true motion, I did not obey; upon which, came all thoſe apparitions which were without, and with them thoſe Spirits which made ſuch excellent melody. Then did that power in me move me to ſtand up as before;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118021:18"/>upon vvhich I fell a vveeping; and much love vvrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, to remain longer in that place of Humility; judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf as unworthy of that Union and Love with God, which before I was a partaker of: then came one of thoſe Apparitions to me, who gave me to underſtand, that all what I was, having been offered as a Pledge, according to the Will of the Pure in me, had wrought in God that affection which formerly he had towards me, upon vvhich I vvas raiſed upon my Feet by the povver of that Spirit in me; my Hands, my Feet, and Body, moved, and acted in their Order, vvithout the leaſt motion or conſent of motion by me: then vvas I highly elevated in my Spirit, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by a voice in me, to Dance vvith thoſe Appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; vvhich I did the remaining part of that night; and by the povver of that Spirit in me, yielding my ſubjection, vvas I toſſed to and fro, and mounted up and dovvn in the obſervation of thoſe Spirits by vvhom I vvas accompanied, as though I had been a Spirit my ſelf.</p>
            <p>It may be obſerved, That about this time it was ſo with me, That what I looked upon, I ſhould be ſearching after knowledge, in relation to it; making enquiry, the cauſe of its Being, the way by which it came to have a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For, I was perſwaded, That the Knowledge of all things was to be Diſcovered and made known to me: ſo that a while after, my prying ſo much after Knowledge, did infuſe ſo much Spirit in me, that I could not look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any thing, but I was tormented in my Spirit at the ſight thereof; and many times had ſuch burnings in my Body, as may be likened to the heat of live Coals, by which, for many nights, I could not have the leaſt reſt.</p>
            <p>Having refrained from Food about a day and a half, I was moved, though limited by the Spirit in me for a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time, to go and eare: So having made a ſearch for the like Food that uſually I did eat, and finding none, but in the ſtead thereof a great Roaſt of Beef; I was at a loſs;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118021:19"/>upon which there aroſe a great Conteſt in my Spirit what I ſhould do; ſaid that Spirit which reſpected me for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying of Nature, Eate of the Beef: ſaid the other Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by which I was limited, No; I am the Lord: ſaid the former, Nay, but eate; ſince there is no other, there is a ſufficient juſtification: Whereupon the Caſe being well examined, after a time Judgement was determined upon that Spirit by which I was limited: So I did take and eat while ſatisfied, with much moderation: All which time being much diſquieted, and ſtrongly moved to give over.</p>
            <p>This Deed being now finiſhed, I went into the Hall, where, after two or three turns, I ſate down, and caſting my Eyes upwards, I was taken with a ſtrong Fancy that I ſaw Heaven open, from whence proceeded a great blaſt of Fire ſomwhat like unto Lightning: at which ſight (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing really perſwaded it was a diſcovery of thoſe Plagues which were to be poured forth upon me, becauſe of the former Diſobedience) I was ſtruck down by that power in me, as though a dead thing had fallen; upon which, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately there was an extream burning within me, like unto the heat of a fiery hot Furnace, which remained a little more than about half a quarter of an hour. About three hours following this, there was a private Meeting of our People, whither I was moved to go, though much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to my Will; but being in a great fear, I durſt not deny, but went: ſo after I had been there about half an hour, I was moved, by the power of that Spirit in me, to ſhake; which manner of ſhaking I had long waited for; believing they were Effects, in order to the rooting out and perfect deſtroying of that Being in me, which was of the Devil: So it being obſerved, that I was moved to ſhake, the Command was, Give way: which ſignified, that I ſhould not limit the Work of the Lord in me upon that which was for Condemnation: ſo I gave way; upon
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118021:19"/>which, the ſtrength of that Spirit by which I was moved to ſhake, grew, ſo that what ſtrength I had in me of my ſelf, was not in the leaſt ſufficient to ſubdue the workings of the other Spirit in, and upon me, whoſe power wrought ſo in me, being ſpread like unto an infuſed ſubſtance into all Parts and Joynts of my Body, that my whole Man was ſo ſhaken, torn, and rent, that had I not by a great ſtrength been enabled, I could not have contained: Alſo, it did work in me, as though I had taken a ſtrong Purge, by which I was clenſed exceedingly, in working forth of me an extream Foam: So having fulfilled its Will, it ceaſed of it ſelf. Now as the Air is rent by the fierceneſs of the Spirit, by which is cauſed a hideous and ratling noiſe, called, Thunder; and ſo the whole Heavens become clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of all filthy vapours, or corrupted ſubſtance, natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtructive to all Beings: ſo was it believed, that the corrupted Spirit in me, was rent and torn by that Spirit which is my Life, by which the Heavens in me, was clenſed. Then was I poſſeſſed with theſe perſwaſions, That this was one of thoſe two Plagues which was to be poured forth upon me; and that the occaſion of this Plague, was, becauſe of the denial of my Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, in the preſence of the Jewiſh Spirits in me, out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to my own Liberty, the ſatisfying of Nature with that Food which was diſallowed.</p>
            <p>After this, (as I remember) the following night, I was Commanded to ſtay up all that night, and wait for Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations: but having refrained from ſleep divers nights be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I could not wait according to the requirings of the Spirit, becauſe of extream drouzineſs: whereupon, I made interceſſion to thoſe Apparitions, to take reſt for that night: ſo upon Promiſe of attending there the next night, I had liberty; but going up ſtairs, a voyce ſpake in me, and willed me to go down: but then I ſuppoſed it to be from one of the Spirits which I left behind me in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118021:20"/>Room: ſo out of great fear, I was enjoyned to ſtay up all that night, and durſt not ſleep, but wait for Revelations: and having waited a ſhort time, I could not poſſibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain longer from reſt: then was I perſwaded to go againſt the Will of the Spirit in me: but in going, it ſpake again, and Commanded me to go in the Shop; which I did: and having waited there about half an hour, wreſtling ſtrongly againſt ſleep, I moved (of my ſelf) to go up again into the Chamber; but going up ſtairs, another voyce ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind me, and Commanded me to return back again: then was I Commanded by that in me, to lie down and humble my ſelf, for I had Blaſphemed: which I did; wallowing, and tumbling upon the ground: Then heard I another voyce, ſaying, <hi>Nicodemus</hi> is in thee, the betrayer of Chriſt in the night: Then ſorrow ſtruck me to the very heart, and I was extreamly troubled: ſo after I had layen about an hours time upon the ground, I was moved by that Being in me to riſe; but as I was riſing, I was commanded to lie down again: Anon after, I was moved to riſe, as before: but when riſing, I was commanded to lie ſtill: and ſo by contradictions of this Spirit in me, was I thus acted divers times: in the end, it was pleaſed to raiſe me on my Feet, it ſelf moving and guiding of my Body by its own power, like as before: So this night being ſpent, I was in the morning commanded to light a Fire with dead Coals and Sticks, (that a Miracle might be made known to be wrought by me;) being really perſwaded, that like as Fire did proceed from the Lord upon the Altar, in the ſight of <hi>Moſes, Aaron,</hi> and the Children of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> So from the Lord, in me, ſhould there proceed that Vertue vvhich ſhould infuſe a heat into thoſe Coals and Sticks, by vvhich a Fire ſhould be kindled; now being confident I ſhould ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the vvork: yea, had I been Maſter of the vvhole world, I ſhould have ventured all, vvith a value of no vvorth, upon the performance of this Deed: having laid all things in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118021:20"/>their order, as directed by that Spirit which moved me to the work, I was moved to blow with my mouth; but in ſhort, blow I did, try one way, then another way, and blowed as ſtrong that poſſible I could; expecting ſtill, that from my Life, the Lord, there ſhould heat proceed with my breath, to the lightning of the fire: but in the end, not being able to effect the thing, I was extreamly troubled, that I the Chriſt of God ſhould fail in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the firſt miracle, ſince ſo many miracles were wrought by him that was a figure of me. Then went I private into the Cellar, and there hearkned to within my ſelf for a command from the Spirit in me, to deſire the apparitions: which being given, they were deſired, and ſo came. Then was made known unto them how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect my performance was in that Service required of me. Upon which was anſwered, That I was not yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: but however, it was the purpoſe of God, that I ſhould be ſerviceable in the healing of the lame, the ſick, the blinde, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſouls, as Chriſt did heal the imperfect parts of the viſible body; and that all the viſible miracles wrought by him, did ſignifie what was to be effected mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous in the inviſible part of every man that ſhould be ſaved by my Doctrine: and ſo they departed.</p>
            <p>Seldom a night after this, for about a week, but I ſtaid up moſt part of all the night, and divers ſtrange things effected by me, or thoſe apparitions, every night: ſo that having deſtroyed the courſe of nature ſo much, in not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of reſt, that for a time following, when I came to have liberty to reſt, I could not, though never ſo deſired. Once, when ſtriving, ſtrugling, mounting, flinging, and throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a conteſt againſt ſleep, I was immediately taken by the power of that Spirit in me, and caſt up againſt the wall; and when ſetled upright, and cloſed to the wall, there was infuſed in me ſuch a freſh ſupply of life, like unto a mighty ſtartle, that all drowzineſs was deſtroyed, and I was a freſh as could be.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:118021:21"/>
            <p>The day following this night, was the firſt day of the week: ſo betimes in the morning, I was moved to go to the place of our Meeting, and there wait until the time of meeting; and, as it was uſual, not purpoſing to come home till the evening; and alſo, much neceſſitated I was moved to eat before I went; ſo having cut a piece of Bread, about a fourth part of a peny-loaf, I began to eat: but when having eaten about half, I was command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to eat no more, but lay the reſt by till the next day: ſo it being undeniable by me, I did obey; and it was my food the following day. Then did I make to the Meeting, where I ſpent my time while the people were gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: in which time, as I was walking in the Garden, a Fly flew in my face; which thing being obſerved, I was moved to examine, what it ſhould mean; ſo by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of this Spirit in me, <hi>I</hi> was confidently perſwaded that it was a Meſſenger from God, the Life in him being believed to be of God, and from that life was he moved to flie in my face; by which was meant a giving me to underſtand ſomething that was required of me by God. From that time was <hi>I</hi> guided by Flyes in many things; being very certain, that they were moved by God in them, to make known what was his will to me.</p>
            <p>Then vvhen the Company came, <hi>I</hi> vvas commanded to ſhevv a humility in me beyond any of theirs, as Chriſt did ſhevv a humility in him beyond any of his Apoſtles. Whereupon <hi>I</hi> vvas commanded to pull off my Band, and then vvas <hi>I</hi> moved to make knovvn unto the people the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that God required in the Creation, vvhich vvas to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their up the ſmall ſticks that vvere ſcattered in the Garden, and lay them by themſelves; and the dry leaves that vvere under the Trees, by themſelves; and the ſmall ſtones that vvere ſcattered in the Walks, by themſelves; and the pieces of Brick, (as <hi>I</hi> remember) if not, ſome ſuch-like, by themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:118021:21"/>
            <p>Now, in the time of this ſervice, I gave over ſometimes by the perſwaſion of divers Friends; but when given o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, I ſhould be commanded, by the firſt Fly that I ſaw, to the ſervice again. Afterwards, being obſerved by one who was a Chief of us, he came to me, and took me by the hand, perſwading me to give over, and go along with him, and hear what was ſpoken by him that was ſpeaking to the people; ſo I gave over. Then when the time of our being there was ended, it was alſo required by him, that I ſhould go with him where he intended to ſpend his time till the Afternoon; which I did: but in the way as we were going, I was mov'd to gather up ſtones as before; and as I was gathering, I ſaw two white round ſtones lie one by the other, at which ſight I was poſſeſſed with a confident belief, by the information of this Spirit in me, that thoſe ſtones came from Heaven, and it was given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me to finde them: then was my minde informed by that in me, that the one ſignified <hi>Eſau,</hi> and the other <hi>Jacob;</hi> ſo I was moved to throw the greateſt of them away, and onely preſerve the leſſer: it was alſo given me to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that this leſſer did not onely ſignifie <hi>Iacob,</hi> but the white Stone ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> which was ſent as a token from Chriſt in Heaven to me; and ſo long as I kept that ſtone I had unity with God; but if loſt, I ſhould be diſ-united. So when we came to that place we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to go, which was a Garden-houſe, we ſate down in the Garden: but after a time, I was moved to do the former work again, where I gathered up ſtones and coles, ſticks and broken corkes, or what I ſaw ſcattered on the ground. So by and by comes into the Garden one whom I much loved, that was of us; and looking him in the face, I was confident in my ſelf, I ſaw death in him: upon which, as I remember, I told him that he was accurſed from God, ſeeing of him much changed; I was really perſwaded by this Spirit in me, that he had ſlain the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118021:22"/>and there was no remedy he muſt die eternally; the plagues of God would be poured forth upon him in this life, and in the life to come.</p>
            <p>A ſhort time after this, as I was at reſt, about mid-night, in a ſlumber between ſleep and wake, I ſaw a viſion of Spirits in the room, by which I was ſtartled exceedingly, and ſate up, being ſtrongly moved to riſe; but being much drowſie, and deſirous of more ſleep, <hi>I</hi> lay down again, and fell aſleep preſently, and then into a dream, that the Chamber-floor ſunk under me, and that <hi>I</hi> was looſed down upon thoſe boards that ſunk under me, through the boards of every Chamber, till <hi>I</hi> came into the Cellar, which is five ſtories high; upon which <hi>I</hi> waked, and ſate ſtill a little inſtant: then was <hi>I</hi> taken with a ſtrange fancy, that the bed was ſinking under me; upon which <hi>I</hi> moved my body, and in moving <hi>I</hi> was poſſeſſed with a fierce com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand by the Being in me, to riſe, and make all the ſpeed that poſſible <hi>I</hi> could into the Kitchin; which being done, <hi>I</hi> was guided by the power of that in me, to turn round; and in turning round, <hi>I</hi> ſaw a light playing upon the wall, at which ſight <hi>I</hi> was moved to ſtand ſtill, and look ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly upon it, ſo, as <hi>I</hi> ſtood looking upon it, it ceaſed: then was <hi>I</hi> poſſeſſed with a great fear, not knowing what that ſignified; (but ſince <hi>I</hi> conceived, the occaſion was the brightneſs of the fire) and in the time of this fear, going to ſit down, <hi>I</hi> was moved to ſtand: immediately upon which, <hi>I</hi> was taken with the ſight of Linens that lay a ſoaking in water, intended by the Maids as a preparative in order to the cleanſing of them; ſo <hi>I</hi> was moved to look as ſtedfaſt upon them that poſſible <hi>I</hi> could: upon which, there came a ſpeedy command from this Being in me, that <hi>I</hi> ſhould lay them in a better order than they were, with this information, that God is the God of order; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, that Chriſt denied not the leaſt ſervice willed of his Father, <hi>I</hi> was the more ſpeedier ſubjected to the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118021:22"/>obedience of this moving; ſo the readineſs of my will to that ſervice required, was accepted of, as though the deed had been effected, and <hi>I</hi> was ſet free: immediate upon which, <hi>I</hi> was guided to look ſtedfaſt upon another object, which was not in that order as <hi>I</hi> judged it ſhould have been: then the like command as before, injoyned me that <hi>I</hi> ſhould effect that ſervice which related to the order of thoſe things, though far more different from that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs properly doth reſpect a man, than the former: but in regard of my ſpeedy condeſcention to the buſineſs, <hi>I</hi> was freed from the performance, as before: then was <hi>I</hi> moved to fit down, and look ſtedfaſtly in the blaze of the Candle, in expectation to be directed in ſome ſervice, by the moving of the blaze to and fro, or by the ſparkles that proceeded forth of it; ſo the blaze of the Candle moved to and fro, and the ſparks were many: but being not able to apprehend what the meaning of the Life ſhould be, by which it was moved to and fro, and occaſioned to ſparkle, <hi>I</hi> was tormented in my ſelf, and ſtamped, and flew up and down the room like a mad man. By and by, when a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle quieted, <hi>I</hi> came to the fire-ſide, and was moved to look in the fire, in expectation to receive ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to ſervice by the flame or ſparks of the fire: ſo after a time being tired by looking in the fire, I caſt my eyes upwards, and ſeeing ſomething ſwim upon a great Kettle of water over the fire, I was taken at the fight thereof, to ſee what it was; and as I ſtood looking upon the water, I was poſſeſſed with a command from that Spirit in me, upon the account of Salvation, that I ſhould put my right hand in the pan of hot water; (giving me to know, that the heat thereof ſhould not ſeiſe upon me:) but (through fear) ſtanding a little inſtant before I performed the command, (as in the twinkling of an eye) I caſt my ſight off the water, and ſeeing ſomething, (as I conceived) falling towards the ground, I looked back again to ſee what it was, and found it to be a black thing like unto a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118021:23"/>great Fly, (which then I took to be a Fly,) whereupon I was taken from the former Service, and Commanded by that in me, to look as fierce as poſſible I could upon that Fly; then was Lenjoyned, by the ſame being in me, to hold my right Leg to the Fire, and obſerve ſtrictly the direction of that Fly, to the burning of it: ſo the Fly moved from the ſame place it was, and ſtood upon the Harth, above a quarter of a yard off the Fire: Now this perſwaſion being firmly wrought in me, That did I not Obey this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, I ſhould be eternally damned; I went ſpeedily cloſe to the Fire, and there held my Right Leg, with both my Hands, the ſame diſtance off the Fire, as it ſtood: ſo the Fly began its work, thus, moving ſomtimes neerer the Fire, ſomtimes farther off; ſomtimes turning the one ſide, ſomtimes the other; ſomtimes round, and ſo to the ſame place again, &amp;c. So, by the ſtrength of that Command in me, was I made plyable to guide my Leg, in the imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of every moving by the Fly: And having ſpent about a third part of an hour in this Service; all which time ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſible of the heat that proceeded from the Fire bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in my Leg, in turning round by the direction of the Fly, I loſt the ſight of him; and then was I freed to go from the Fire. Afterward it was made known unto me, by that in me, That this was the other of the two Plagues. Then going to ſee what work was made by the Fire in my Leg, I was taken with a ſtrong perſwaſion, That the ſame Spirit in me, by whom I was moved to burn it, would, by the power of himſelf, heal it; ſo that for ſeveral dayes I durſt not make it known to any man, though it was bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the Knee to the Foot; and then was the time come of my Perfection, as was made known to me by the Apparitions: ſo about noon of the ſame day, being about my imployment, I was moved to give over; but not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the motion preſent, there came divers Flyes and reſted upon that Buſineſs I had in hand; by which I was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118021:23"/>I had offended in not readily Obeying: ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving left my employment, I was moved, by the power of that in me, to Wraſtle and War with my ſelf three times, which I did, like a mad diſtracted man: and when it was done, it was given me to underſtand, that this was a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration againſt my Suffering; and it had a reſpect to that Agony which Chriſt was in before his Death. Then was I moved to ſtand ſtill; and having ſtood a little inſtant, I was directed by this Spirit, To look about me: and as I was looking, I ſaw a Needle ſtuck in my Sleeve; which Needle I was moved to take in my Hand, and thruſt both Ends through my two Thumbs, which I did with what ſpeed poſſibly I could: firſt, the one End to the Bone of the one Thumb; and afterwards, the other End to the Bone of the other Thumb: and there being no paſſage for the Needle through the Bones, the Needle was bent in the cloſing of my Thumbs together: Then was I commanded ſpeedily, that I ſhould ſtand upon a Box, by the Wall, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout half a yard off the Ground; which being done, I was directed to turn my Back to the Wall, and ſpread my Hands one upon the other, with the Needle remaining in my Thumbs, ſo wide that I could, and ſo lift my Arms over my Head, and then to ſtrain my Arms and Body as high as poſſible <hi>I</hi> could, with the Backs of my Hands joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Wall. All which being done, I was to liken a Death upon the Croſs: ſo I gave way to a Drouzineſs (as though I was a dying) and by and by I fell down upon the Ground, as though dead: But, before I lay as in the Grave, I was moved to ſpread over me Shavings of white Paper that lay by on the Floor; (by which was meant the Covering of me with white Sheets:) then to tye a Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchief about my Head: ſo in regard of my ſpeed, (and not heeding, but making as though I were dead,) in the tying of my Handkerchief, I tore much of my Hair off: This being done, I lay upon my Back minding nothing,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118021:24"/>like as in a ſleep:) and having lain there about three quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of an hour, in imitation of three dayes, (the time of Chriſts being in the Grave) I was immediately, by the power of that Spirit in me, raiſed on my Feet, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, with all the ſpeed that poſſibly I could, to make to that place, where the Miniſters, that were of us, with divers more, were; and give them knowledge of what was done: and then to make choice of ſome of them to be my Apoſtles; and ſo ſpeedily to go abroad into all the world and Preach the Goſpel. So I took my Cloak, and ran forth, in expectation to flie by the power of <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel, which was believed to be then in me, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as before was promiſed:) but being then diſappointed of Ability to flie, I was much troubled: upon which, there came a ſpecial command, that I ſhould pull off my Shoes; which I did inſtantly: (and turning my Cloak under my Arm, I threw my Shoes in my Cloak) and ſo made away with all the might I could: (and verily, I am perſwaded, were I now to run for a Kingdom, I could not make two thirds of that ſpeed I did then.) Now the Houſe being in Moor-fields, and the path-way to the Houſe being of a little compaſs, I was cauſed to leap over the Railes, and alſo run over much Linen that lay Whiting upon the Graſs, becauſe of the fierceneſs of my ſpeed. So,</p>
            <p>When I came to the place, I gave them to underſtand, That Chriſt (meaning my ſelf) was Riſen from the Dead, &amp;c. ſhewing the Holes that were made in my Thumbs with the Needle: upon which, I was looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with a ſtrange haſty look; and charged to be ſilent, for I was in Darkneſs; the Witneſſes of God were ſlain in me. So there being many there, and all of them judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me with one Conſent, I was ſilenced: Upon which, they ſpake lovingly to me; and bad me to ſit down; and put on my Shoes: which being done, I made known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, that my Leg was burned, and the way by which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118021:24"/>it came to be burned; then was there care taken by them for the healing of my leg: but in regard it had been kept unknown before, it was much corrupted, and (as I remember) about a quarter of a year before it was cured; much of which time <hi>I</hi> was conſtrained to keep my Bed; and ſo, not having the Liberty of my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, my Spirit was kept the ſtiller, and the means of my Recovery out of that ſad Condition which I was in, was the more effectual.</p>
            <p>Now being incenſed by what was ſpoken from them, and the ſtrangeneſs of their Spirits towards what moved in me to ſpeak or to act, that I was in darkneſs, the light by which I was enlightned, being put out, ſo that I had not a ſavory diſcerning of what was good, and what was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; and alſo, when ſeriouſly conſidering of divers acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which I was ſubjected to by the teachings of this Spirit, that they were deſtructive to my being, I was the more concerned in what was given me to underſtand by them.</p>
            <p>Then was I in a ſad condition, not knowing what I ſhould do, that I might be redeemed from this body of ſin, and death.</p>
            <p>So I was directed by them to wait a time, and keep in my minde, not giving heed unto any thing but what had a reſpect unto my neceſſary imployment: which I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to do, but could not for a time, being ſo full of this Spirit, by which I was tormented day and night, through the ſtrength of imagination upon things without me, and alſo by the power of it ſelf in me, and many times with extream fiery burnings in my Spirit.</p>
            <p>So in labouring to keep in my minde, this Spirit in me came to be ſilenced in his motions, and weakned of his ſtrength; by which his union with thoſe Spirits without me, was ſeparated: and ſo I was freed from their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, being reſiſted, they flew away.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118021:25"/>
            <p>Now for a time this body of ſin remained living in me, by which I was tormented as before ſpoken; and then, being not fed with my ſervice, the ſtrength of that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which is my Life, having raiſed a war againſt him, utterly deſtroyed, burned up, and confumed his whole Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, (as is declared following.)</p>
            <p>About two months after, it was given me to underſtand, that I was in a deluſion: as I was going along the ſtreet, I met one that was of us, who told me, That <hi>he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieved a Letter forth of the Country from a Friend that was a Teacher:</hi> ſo he asked me the Queſtion, <hi>Whether he were beſt to open it the next meeting, (which was on a private day) or forbear until the firſt day:</hi> ſo it was anſwered in the cloſe of our diſcourſe, <hi>Do as thou wilt.</hi> But when parted, there was a voice ſpake in me, ſaying, <hi>Do as thou art moved;</hi> which ſtrongly tempted me to go back again, and unſpeak that word <hi>Wilt,</hi> and place in the ſtead thereof <hi>Moved,</hi> being perſwaded that I had offended in ſpeaking that word, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the will of man was to be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>The next day being called to Dinner, I refuſed, in regard I had eat ſomething that day before: whereupon there aroſe in me an exceeding joy, which I was not able to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due; the cauſe was conceived, becauſe of my obedience to the Pure in me, The ſame day in the Afternoon, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Meeting, I was moved to eat two ſmall Apples that I had in my pocket; but firſt I waited a time, that a patient, gentle, and pure Spirit might guide me in the eating of them: then, when going to eat them, I was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that two was too much at once, believing, that that Spirit which moved me to eat ſo much, was a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer of the Creation: ſo I reſolved to eat but one, and retain the other to diſpoſe of to a Friend at the Meeting: upon which there aroſe the like joy in me as before; then did I conclude, that ſurely the Lord was well pleaſed with me, becauſe of the tenderneſs that I had towards the Pure
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118021:25"/>in me: for in regard of the deſparate caſe I was in, I was tender of every thing that I ſpeak or acted.</p>
            <p>So the following day about the evening, immediately there ſprang forth of me thoughts, ſo faſt as one could fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the other, without the leaſt moving by me to think any thing, (then began the deſtruction of the body of ſin) and ſo thoſe thoughts remained, flying abroad in the Air every moment, ſo faſt as could be, while about two or three dayes: and then immediately as before, concerning Thoughts, there aroſe a ſpeaking in my minde, ſo faſt, as one word could be expreſſed after another: ſo thoſe Thoughts and Speaking in my minde continued every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of time (as I remember) about two months; and all along as time went away, that Being which thought and ſpake ſink'd deeper in my minde, till in the end they were ſwallowed up in victory: but from that time of a about two months, they began to ceaſe a little, about one or two hours at divers times in a day, and ſo as time came on, they ceaſed by degrees, while at laſt I could have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained an hour or two together without any thing in my Minde, or the leaſt Thought; and in the end, ſometimes a whole day, with very few Thoughts, or any thing in my Minde: then came I to witneſs a Redeemer from that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of ſin that lived in me.</p>
            <p>Now in the whole time of this ſpeaking in my Minde, and flying abroad of my Thoughts, I laboured according to the teaching of my own Spirit, to keep in my Minde, for the deſtroying of theſe Thoughts and Speaking; ſo by the power of that which was low in the Mind, the Meek &amp; the Humble, like as a Lamb and a Lion, gentle and ſtrong, was the ſtrength of this ſin ſubdued; and by that Light which ſaw it, was there a fire kindled, by which it was deſtroyed and burned up, and the aſhes blown away like chaff before the winde.</p>
            <p>In all this time of the war, every Member were Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118021:26"/>againſt me, whatever my Minde was taken with, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſeeing, in hearing, in ſmelling, in taſting, in feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what was minded by any of my Sences, this evil One in me, would be raiſing of Thoughts in things of the like Nature.</p>
            <p>So almoſt a years time having been ſpent amongſt theſe people, with exceeding zeal in their way, acted forth from ſuch a Love that may not be expreſſed, and very ſtrict in the performance of every of theſe Ceremonies before ſpoken, when being, through rich Grace &amp; abundant Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, in ſome meaſure reſtored unto the like enjoyment I had, before I knew any thing of them, through a great provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, the Lord was pleaſed to enlighten my Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by the manifeſtation of what was according to himſelf in me, compared with what was given forth from himſelf, recorded in his Scripture, (the manner of which is declared following) ſo that weakneſs which ruled and reigned in me, and by which I was ſubjected to the performance of thoſe Ceremonial Practiſes, being made known by the Truth which abides for ever, I was freed from the former Obedience, by which as a ſlave I was kept in bondage, through much deceit, covered with a voluntary Humility, worſhipping therein I knew not what. Whereupon, there was occaſioned a bitter envy in them againſt me; ſo that with greateſt violence they took to themſelves that power of judging me to be a <hi>Judas,</hi> a Betrayer of the innocent; and that wherein I was ſeparated from them, therein was I joyned unto an Harlot, which Harlot they denied: giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me to know, That the Plagues of God would conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually follow me: which Condemnation I muſt own; for I was turned out to among the wilde Beaſts, in the broad way, which way did lead unto eternal Death.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and many ſuch-like terrible judging Expreſſions, were made known unto me, by a noiſe from a Chief of them: but foraſmuch as the ſame Nature lived in me for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118021:26"/>a time, by which I was not onely acted to judge all men that were not of us, to be reprobated from the knowledge of the Truth, and ſo accurſed from God, with what judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment followeth thoſe who are in ſuch a condition; but I abhorred the very ſight of Men: ſo that I knew the ground in him from whence this judging of me did ariſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was minded to let paſs what was ſpoken, judging better things of him, and that through the weakneſs of his Underſtanding, out of a ſimplicity of Love to the Truth, and good intents towards me, was he thus moved to ſpeak of me.</p>
            <p>Now all this time of my being amongſt this people, I durſt not declare any thing of my minde unto any, but thoſe of us, or hearken unto any thing ſpoken by any, which bear Teſtimony againſt any thing practiſed by us: ſo that I came not to ſee what might be offered from any, as an Objection againſt thoſe Ceremonies looked upon as ſubſtantials in performances.</p>
            <p>But afterwards, ſeeing a Friend at the Meeting (which was of us) whom I had not ſeen for a time; whoſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding was enlightned touching many things which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly he was ſubjected unto, though not known unto me: So after ſome paſſages between us, he began to ſpeak ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning thoſe words, Thee and Thou: intending to bring me to underſtand, what that was in me, by which I was guided to the performance of them: and being wary leſt I ſhould apprehend in him a diſlike, touching the uſing of them, and ſo occaſion a diſturbance in me; he brought his Diſcourſe ſo about, that it was required I ſhould give an Information of what was manifeſted in me, touching the Evil that lay in the not performance of them; though not by way of Queſtion: So having examined with my ſelf, I gave him Anſwer, That the word You, did reſpect more than One; But the words, Thee and Thou, were the true Engliſh words; ſo that that minde by which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118021:27"/>the words were removed out of their places, was the pride in Man, which Nature ſtood in the Fall; and therefore it was not to be fed: but as though in a pretence of holding a contrary Argument, He Diſcourſed with me for the word You, and not the words Thee and Thou; eſpecially in ſome caſes. One ground of his Argument was, <hi>Give no offence to Iew nor Gentile, nor the Church of God, all which kept the Peace, to thoſe that could bear them, the words Thee and Thou; but to thoſe that could not, the word You.</hi> So after ſome time of Diſcourſe upon theſe words, he ſpake in the ſame kind, as though by contraries, concerning taking off the Hat, and civil Reſpect between man and man, with the reſt of thoſe things refuſed by us: but there being not a ſufficiency in me to Anſwer what was ſpoken by him; I told him, That I was Convinced in my ſelf, and ſo I was moved from the Lord in what I did, but could not make out to his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what was my Convincement. Then he gave me to underſtand, <q>That he did not witneſs a Command for the uſing of thoſe Ceremonies, though formerly in his own Will, out of imitation, they were practiſed by him: but when he witneſſed a Command, then he ſhould Obey.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now being diſquieted, in regard of his perfect Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Unity of Spirit, which formerly he owned with us, we parted at variance: but after his departure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſſetled as touching them, by what was ſpoken from him, I went privately, and examined with my ſelf, how I came to take them up, and what it was that upheld their reign in me: ſo finding that my will was the firſt cauſe, I went to divers that were of us, and contrary to my mind, I held an Argument, as though I owned thoſe things, which formerly with them I denied, that I might learn from them what Reaſon or Ground they could declare, to the deſtroying of my pretended Judgement: ſo after ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining the Scriptures, &amp; much diſcourſe, I found not only ſome inclination of their Belief in reſpect of them, but
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118021:27"/>a real convincement in my ſelf. And ſo after a ſhort time, through the Mercy of God, I came to ſee, not onely a death of that extraordinary, imaginary, and deviliſh Spirit, by which I was ſo extreamly deluded; but alſo the weakneſs of that in me, which through a Cloak of Righteouſneſs debarred me of my living and converſing with men, as I had done formerly in the way of my livelihood: and now I affirm, from the Truth of God, manifeſted in me, that through a ſlaviſh Fear, that I was in bondage unto, I was, as others are, kept in thoſe Deluſions; and that there is no more ſin, in the not uſing of theſe Ceremonies, than in the uſing of them; provided, that wiſdom guides.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>MUch time hath bin ſpent ſeriouſly in the Examination of every particular herein declared; but the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof might occaſion many ſerious Minds to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Truth of it: but I ſolemnly affirm, in the preſence of the Eternal God, before whom all things are manifeſt, that with a clear Underſtanding in the ſence of my Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, while under thoſe Temptations and powers of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, I have endeavoured to make known the Truth in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of Minde. And the God of Truth beareth me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, That (to my knowledge) I lye not in any thing ſpoken: alſo, much of this might be juſtified by many Eye-Witneſſes. True, it is matter of Admiration, and alſo, greatly might it be admired, that the goodneſs of God ſhould ſo far exceed the depths of Satan, and the powers of Darkneſs, as that the deceitful workings of this evil One ſhould be made manifeſt, and that by the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of his Grace, through his abundant Love, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes rejoyceth in Mercy, after ſo great an Apoſtacie from himſelf, he ſhould reſtore his own Heritage to the place of their abode, and ſettle the Underſtanding, the Minde, and Affections of his loſt Creature, upon the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118021:28"/>Foundation-Rock, which will abide when all things elſe muſt periſh. Praiſes to his Name for ever; and all whoſe Mindes are united to the upright and faithful Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and ſtaid therein, let them ſay with me, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſince the Lord hath appeared ſo mightily towards me, in reſtoring from the Death, and in raiſing out from the Grave, the Light of himſelf, by which my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is better eſtabliſhed than before; it may be judged acceptable, and deſirous, to know what the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Faith is now.</p>
               <p>I ſay, The Scriptures they do diſcover the Minde and Will of God, and they are profitable to the edifying of all, under what eſtare or condition ſoever: but the Will of God is in part made manifeſt in all, not only by what hath been learned from that Diſcovery of Truth in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, but where the Scriptures is not.</p>
               <p>And by this inviſible Law written in the Hearts of all Men, are Men convinced of every ſecret Temptation, which luſteth in them to evil (if giving heed unto it:) and as this Law-giver in us, is ſpiritual, ſo that Miniſtration of Righteouſneſs in us, is ſpiritual; and that Obedience which it requireth, is in Spirit and in Truth; by which, thoſe that give heed unto it, are, and may be guided, out of all the Works of the Fleſh, above the Law, into a poſſeſſion of that Covenant which giveth Life, and ſo witneſs a new Birth, born of the Spirit: (without which, there is no entrance into the Kingdom, as ſaith the Scripture, <q>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a Man be born again, of Water and of the Spirit, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God</q>) and then will thoſe Covenants be made manifeſt, and fulfilled, which ſaith, <hi>Unto ſuch who fear my Name, ſhall the ſon of righteouſneſs ariſe with healing in his wings: and he ſhall turn the heart of the children to their fathers, and the heart of the fathers to their children: And ye ſhall be all taught of God from the greateſt unto the leaſt; ſo that you need not ſay one to another, Know the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:118021:28"/>Lord. And I will write my law in their hearts, and place my fear in their inward parts, that they ſhall not depart from me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now where the righteouſneſs of the Law is fulfilled, there is God made manifeſt; and ſo far as that Obedience which it requireth, rules in man, ſo far have they Unity with God.</p>
               <p>But yet, I do not ſay, That the Scriptures are in the leaſt to be diſeſteemed, but great is the advantage of theſe who have them to aſſiſt in the wayes of God, which guide to God.</p>
               <p>For much was the profit of the Jews before the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, in that the Oracles of God were committed unto them, the Law &amp; the Prophets being made known to and amongſt them, which the Gentiles had not: but now far greater is the benefit, or if diſobeyed the juſt Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe, who have the Scriptures more plain to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difying of them, in the Way, in the Truth, in the Life, which is of Chriſt, and leads to himſelf, than ever the Jews had before Chriſt was manifeſted in the world.</p>
               <p>But ſurely greater deceit was never made manifeſt, than is now; the unclean thing having bewitched and darkned the Underſtandings of Men ſo mightily. True, it hath been his buſineſs alwayes to remove the Obedience re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by God of Man, and ſo diſquiet their peaceable enjoyment, that he might ingraft a rebellious Nature, in or upon that Tree which God hath made, on purpoſe to bring forth the Fruits of himſelf to make known his name in: but now the ſubtilty of his workings are far more admired by them in whom he hath taken place, than ever before: for when before the will of God was ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered in the Scriptures, to the view of the world, as it hath been ſince Chriſt and the Apoſtles dayes, much of that hold for his deceit which he hath now, was not.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who lived by the Faith of the Son of God,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118021:29"/>whoſe Habitation was with Chriſt in God, who were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus, who witneſſed Revelations, in whom was eſtabliſhed the Life of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, that new Name, Immortality, which abideth for ever: thoſe, I ſay, ſpeaking forth myſteries which men by wiſdom cannot know, though not my ſteries to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who lived or doth live in the wiſdom of God: but men in their own wiſdom, even ſenſual men, who have not the Spirit, going about to comprehend thoſe things which they enjoy not, they drowned their underſtanding, and darkned their ſight; and ſo the eyes of their Mindes being blinded, they of themſelve wreſt the Scriptures to their own condemnation.</p>
               <p>But to my underſtanding, (and great is my miſtake, if the Spirit of God doth not bear me witneſs herein) where the minde is ſtaid in that Truth which is manifeſt plainly in and unto all men, and be guided thereby in faithfulneſs, and reſpecting nothing before that Obedience which is required by it, ſurely therein God will be glorified, for his Grace hath appeared to all men, and he requireth no more than what he hath given, onely Grace for Grace; and he that abides herein, needs not deſire to dive beyond him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, thinking thereby to apprehend that knowledge which is acceptable, though in the ſight of God accurſed; but in time he will witneſs a Comforter which will lead him out of the Spirit of this world, into the beginning, where all Truth is made manifeſt: and when in joying the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and living in the ſame Life, which the upright and true Servants of the Lord hath done, then will thoſe myſteries of God which are hid from the fleſhly wiſdom, be made known, Life and Immortality being raiſed to Light, and ſo being ſtaid in a ſound minde, the glory of the Lord will be ſeen to the peace of his: and ſurely if the Lord pleaſe to reprove, convince, and correct the wandrings of ſuch as are gone aſtray from him, and have exalted themſelves
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118021:29"/>upon the Mountains, (being lifted up above all what is called God) and guide them to wait thus upon himſelf, there needs no fear, but the bleſſing which he hath reſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his Choſen, even the eternal reſt with himſelf, ſhall be their reward.</p>
               <p>Whereas it hath been ſpoken, That I was not right principled in the way of the Quakers, (ſo called) and that I had not a clear underſtanding of what their Miniſtery held forth: I ſay, deceit ſpeaks in thoſe who thus report of me: for before I was perſwaded to comply with them, I had a right Knowledge of their Belief and Practiſe; but the occaſion by which I became to be loſt in my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and ſo diſtracted and confuſed in Mind, may be obſerved in divers particulars before ſpoken: yet for the Truth ſake I ſhall diſcover the thing more plainer.</p>
               <p>But firſt I ſhall ſpeak a little of what condition I was in before I came amongſt them.</p>
               <p>Having been very zealouſly affected in divers wayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, there was begotten in me much fleſhly wiſdom, in w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> my hope did much reſt, (believing it was the myſtery and wiſdom of the holy Spirit revealed unto me) by which I was perſwaded, that the true worſhip of God, was a true endeavouring to live up to that Obedience w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the outward Law required, &amp; wherein I failed of what this Law requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, (that Doctrine I was learned in continually laboured to perſwade me, that) Chriſt which died at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> had perfected for me; and ſo I was not under the Covenant of Works, but under the Covenant of Grace.</p>
               <p>Yet nevertheleſs, all this time I could not enjoy a true peace, but was greatly diſſatisfied with my Condition; ſometimes being perſwaded that I was out of the Faith, a Reprobate, a Caſt-away, being out of the Election; and other times, when covered over with deceit, I ſhould glory in my condition.</p>
               <p>Now, when being fully perſwaded, by what I learned
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118021:30"/>from theſe People, (before named) that the Truth indeed was to be found in us, which Truth was made known by the Light in us; which Light, as it was ſpiritual, (if fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing it) it would guide out of all the works of the fleſh, to the worſhipping of God in Spirit and in Truth; I was then to begin a new Religion, and to loſe all that ever I learned before, all that Wiſdom, that Knowledge, Faith, Hope, Love, Zeal, <hi>&amp;c</hi> which before I hoped in, and ſo to wait out of my own Thoughts and Imagination, as in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Miniſtration of Condemnation, (which was to paſs upon all that which was of fleſh) by which the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was to be renewed; and as Death paſſed upon the one, Life was to be reſtored unto the other, until a new Birth was brought forth, from which would proceed the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Righteouſneſs unto Holineſs, the end of which, (as ſaith the Scriptures) is eternal Life.</p>
               <p>My Underſtanding being now thus opened, I was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed with much Joy in the ſenſe of that Love I had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and was in hopes to enjoy; and on the other ſide, I was incenſed with much Fear, leſt I ſhould be careleſs, and ſo loſe my way in the Wilderneſs, before I came to the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> and alſo, leſt I ſhould die before I witneſſed the firſt Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>Whereupon, <hi>I</hi> was reſolved to give all diligence that my Calling and Election might be made ſure; but being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally of a very haſty forward Minde, and my Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in part, being a Covenant of my own, there was ſpeedily begotten in me an extream fiery Zeal, ſo that (in the general) I was haſtily carried for the before the true Light, by which in a ſhort time I became loſt in my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; and then, being to ſeek in the wilderneſs, the Diſputer was raiſed to Life, and ſo exalted it ſelf mightily, pleading the cauſe of his people: upon w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>, there was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed a deſperate War; in w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> diviſion the Enemy which was for Condemnation, (having darkned the Light of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118021:30"/>Sun) formed it ſelf in the ſhape of a true Light: and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit having gotten the power to bear rule in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> my mind was led forth out of the true Obedience, (as is before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated) by which the ſimple became exceedingly deceived; but when, after it had finiſhed his courſe, and I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to a right Underſtanding, it is known that no weapon formed againſt the Juſt did proſper, but my Life was as a clear Light, in the ſight of thoſe amongſt whom I was known, being guided in that Obedience, which was profeſſed by thoſe people amongſt whom I was.</p>
               <p>This may reprove the Gain-ſayer; for my witneſs therein is true.</p>
               <p>Such who may be diſſatisfied with any thing contained herein, might judge of me, otherwiſe then they ought, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thoſe hands by whom what I have written is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced: I therefore declare, that before any of them had the leaſt knowledge of my purpoſe, I had writ of my ſelf, (being perſwaded it concerned me as a Duty, chiefly for thoſe Reaſons before ſpoken) but when after ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time that this diſcourſe was wholly perfected, I was perſwaded in what I have done, that ſo ſuch ſerious mindes as might queſtion the Truth of any thing contained in it, might the better receive a ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Since my ſeparation from theſe people, there hath been diſperſed abroad concerning me divers ſcandalous and falſe abuſive reports, by which, where it hath taken place, <hi>I</hi> am preſented as a lewd perſon, changed from whatever it is known <hi>I</hi> have been: but unto the Truth am <hi>I</hi> made manifeſt; by which Truth in me, and in all thoſe that thus have ſpoken and do ſpeak againſt me, am <hi>I</hi> juſtified: which Truth is, and will be the Condemnation of what is believed or ſpoken touching me untruly. True, ſince it pleaſed the Father to make known the excellency of his power in the raiſing out of nothing this body, that the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of himſelf, amongſt other of his works, might
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:118021:31"/>therein appear compleat, both in Body and in Spirit, to the glory of himſelf, and to the praiſe of his Name: <hi>I</hi> ſay, ſince the beginning of this Creation of God, a diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Mind hath appeared in me, againſt that Will, &amp; that Grace, which God hath, as his Law, made known in, and to me; and <hi>I</hi> have amongſt others many times rejected the offers of Grace by the preſumptuous reſolvedneſs of my own peremptory will: ſo that <hi>I</hi> cannot juſtifie my ſelf, yet am I bold wherein I am made free in the ſight of God, being witneſſed by the Spirit of Truth. Falſe reports and good reports muſt paſs, but my Witneſs liveth for ever. I know, and have heard of many which were of them that were convinced in themſelves of much deluſion they lay under; and ſo their Underſtandings being enlightned, they were reformed in their Judgements; but not one of theſe have I known or heard, that have not received from them the like Judgement, and ſcandalous untrue reports, that have been given forth concerning me. Wherefore, by right according to their Law, though falſe, I muſt come under the ſame Condemnation with them. But herein is my Peace, the Word of Truth bearing me witneſs againſt all deceitful Lyes.</p>
               <trailer>The end.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
